<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!--
 *
 * This help file was generated from libsvm_partest.sci using help_from_sci().
 *
 -->

<refentry version="5.0-subset Scilab" xml:id="libsvm_partest" xml:lang="en"
          xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
          xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
          xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
          xmlns:ns3="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
          xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
          xmlns:scilab="http://www.scilab.org"
          xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">

  <refnamediv>
    <refname>libsvm_partest</refname>
    <refpurpose>This function calculate the performance, based on Bayes theorem, of a clinical test.</refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>


<refsynopsisdiv>
   <title>Calling Sequence</title>
   <synopsis>
   libsvm_partest(X)
   </synopsis>
</refsynopsisdiv>

<refsection>
   <title>Parameters</title>
   <variablelist>
   <varlistentry><term>X :</term>
      <listitem><para>is a  2x2 matrix</para></listitem></varlistentry>
   <varlistentry><term>Outputs:</term>
      <listitem><para> </para></listitem></varlistentry>
   <varlistentry><term>:</term>
      <listitem><para>- Prevalence of disease</para></listitem></varlistentry>
   <varlistentry><term>:</term>
      <listitem><para>- Test Sensibility with 95% confidence interval</para></listitem></varlistentry>
   <varlistentry><term>:</term>
      <listitem><para>- Test Specificity with 95% confidence interval</para></listitem></varlistentry>
   <varlistentry><term>:</term>
      <listitem><para>- False positive and negative proportions</para></listitem></varlistentry>
   <varlistentry><term>:</term>
      <listitem><para>- Youden's Index</para></listitem></varlistentry>
   <varlistentry><term>:</term>
      <listitem><para>- Test Accuracy</para></listitem></varlistentry>
   <varlistentry><term>:</term>
      <listitem><para>- Mis-classification Rate</para></listitem></varlistentry>
   <varlistentry><term>:</term>
      <listitem><para>- Positive predictivity with 95% confidence interval</para></listitem></varlistentry>
   <varlistentry><term>:</term>
      <listitem><para>- Positive Likelihood Ratio</para></listitem></varlistentry>
   <varlistentry><term>:</term>
      <listitem><para>- Negative predictivity with 95% confidence interval</para></listitem></varlistentry>
   <varlistentry><term>:</term>
      <listitem><para>- Negative Likelihood Ratio</para></listitem></varlistentry>
   <varlistentry><term>:</term>
      <listitem><para>- Error odds ratio</para></listitem></varlistentry>
   <varlistentry><term>:</term>
      <listitem><para>- Diagnostic odds ratio</para></listitem></varlistentry>
   <varlistentry><term>:</term>
      <listitem><para>- Discriminant Power</para></listitem></varlistentry>
   <varlistentry><term>:</term>
      <listitem><para>- Test bias</para></listitem></varlistentry>
   <varlistentry><term>:</term>
      <listitem><para>- Number needed to Diagnose (NDD)</para></listitem></varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
</refsection>

<refsection>
   <title>Description</title>
   <para>
X is the following 2x2 matrix.
<para>  <informaltable border="1">
<tr>
<td> </td>
<td>Affected(D+)</td>
<td>Healthy(D-)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Positive Test(T+)</td>
<td>True  positives</td>
<td>False positive</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Negative Test(T-)</td>
<td>False negative</td>
<td>True  negatives</td>
</tr>
</informaltable>
</para>
   </para>
   <para>
Sensitivity and Specificity
   </para>
   <para>
The Sensitivity is the probability that the test is positive on sick subjects: P(T+|D+)
The Specificity is the probability that the test is negative on healthy subjects: P(T-|D-)
   </para>
   <para>
Positive and Negative predictivity
   </para>
   <para>
Positive predictivity is the probability that a subject is sick when test is positive: P(D+|T+)
Negative predictivity is the probability that a subject is healthy when test is negative: P(D-|T-)
Positive predictivity=Precision
   </para>
   <para>
Youden's Index
   </para>
   <para>
Youden's J statistics (also called Youden's index) is a single statistic that
captures the performance of a diagnostic test. The use of such a single index
is "not generally to be recommended". It is equal to the risk difference for a
dichotomous test and it defined as: J = Sensitivity + Specificity - 1.
A perfect test has J=1.
   </para>
   <para>
Positive and Negative Likelihood Ratio
   </para>
   <para>
When we decide to order a diagnostic test, we want to know which test (or
tests) will best help us rule-in or rule-out disease in our patient.  In the
language of clinical epidemiology, we take our initial assessment of the
likelihood of disease (“pre-test probability”), do a test to help us shift our
suspicion one way or the other, and then determine a final assessment of the
likelihood of disease (“post-test probability”).
Likelihood ratios tell us how much we should shift our suspicion for a
particular test result. Because tests can be positive or negative, there are at
least two likelihood ratios for each test.  The “positive likelihood ratio”
(LR+) tells us how much to increase the probability of disease if the test is
positive, while the “negative likelihood ratio” (LR-) tells us how much to
decrease it if the test is negative.
You can also define the LR+ and LR- in terms of sensitivity and specificity:
LR+ = sensitivity / (1-specificity)
LR- = (1-sensitivity) / specificity
   </para>
   <para>
Accuracy and Mis-classification rate
   </para>
   <para>
The Accuracy (or Power) is the probability that the test correctly classifies
the subjects; the Mis-classification rate is its complement to 1.
In statistics, the F1 score (also F-score or F-measure) is a measure of a
test's accuracy. It considers both the Precision (positive predictivity)
and the Sensitivity of the test to compute the score:
P is the number of correct results divided by the number of all returned results
S is the number of correct results divided by the number of results that should
have been returned.
The F1 score can be interpreted as a weighted average of the Precision and
Sensitivity, where an F1 score reaches its best value at 1 and worst score at 0.
   </para>
   <para>
Test Bias (TB)
   </para>
   <para>
A test which shows provable and systematic differences in the results of people
based on group membership. For example, a test might be considered biased if
members of one particular gender or race consistently and systematic have
statistically different results from the rest of the testing population.
It is defined as (T+)/(D+)=(TP+FP)/(TP+FN)
A perfect test has a TB=1;
If TB&lt;1 the test underestimates the disease because there are more affected than positive test
If TB&gt;1 the test overestimates the disease because there are more positive test than affected
   </para>
   <para>
Error Odds Ratio.
   </para>
   <para>
Indicates if the probability of being wrongly classified is highest in the
diseased or in the non-diseased group. If the error odds is higher than one the
probability is highest in the diseased group (and the specificity of the test
is better than the sensitivity), if the value is lower than one the probability
of an incorrect classification is highest in the non-diseased group (and the
sensitivity of the test is better than the specificity).
It is defined as (Sensitivity/(1-Sensitivity))/(Specificity/(1-Specificity));
   </para>
   <para>
Diagnostic Odds Ratio.
   </para>
   <para>
Often used as a measure of the discriminative power of the test. Has the value
one if the test does not discriminate between diseased and not diseased. Very
high values above one means that a test discriminates well. Values lower than
one mean that there is something wrong in the application of the test.
It is defined as (Sensitivity/(1-Sensitivity))/((1-Specificity)/Specificity);
   </para>
   <para>
Discriminant power
   </para>
   <para>
The discriminant power for a test, also termed the test effectiveness, is a
measure of how well a test distinguishes between affected and unaffected
persons. It is the sum of logs of Sensivity and Specificity over own false
proportion, scaled by the standard deviation of the logistic normal
distribution curve (square root of 3 divided by π). Test effectiveness is
interpreted as the standardized distance between the means for both populations.
A test with a discriminant value of 1 is not effective in discriminating between affected and unaffected individuals.
A test with a discriminant value of 3 is effective in discriminating between affected and unaffected individuals.
   </para>
   <para>
   </para>
   <para>
</para>
</refsection>

<refsection>
   <title>Examples</title>
   <programlisting role="example"><![CDATA[

X=[80 3; 5 20];
libsvm_partest(X)
   ]]></programlisting>
</refsection>

<refsection>
   <title>See also</title>
   <simplelist type="inline">
   <member><link linkend="libsvm_rocplot">libsvm_rocplot</link></member>
   <member><link linkend="libsvm_confmat">libsvm_confmat</link></member>
   </simplelist>
</refsection>

<refsection>
   <title>Authors</title>
   <simplelist type="vert">
   <member>Created by Giuseppe Cardillo           giuseppe.cardillo-edta@poste.it</member>
   <member>H. Nahrstaedt - 2012</member>
   </simplelist>
</refsection>
</refentry>
